Welcome back.
In this lesson, we are going to see how to use the free ATA's middle were with our SDM 32 to keep mix
when to create a new project from Yeah.
For You project.
Again, the microcontroller.
That doesn't matter.
It should work the same way on all SDM 32 boards.
I'm gonna select my board here.
SDM 32 for one one.
And for this experiment, I'm going to select the nuclear board.
Say no.
Over here.
And then I'll play all pins, pin out.
Clap your notes over here like this.
Oh, say yes.
We can start off by enabling the 80s and the push button for experiment.
I'll go to P five so the two GPL you output and P.S. 13 as GPL you input like this.
So to enable free ATA's, we come to a middle way over here.
And then we select free our tires.
And then we can select the interface here.
Are we use it seems as if you one or V2.
So I'll just select Simms's for you one over here.
And then it enabled it.
Right.
Oh, so what I'm going to do is I'm going to enable to you Art, so that we can use that in a way experiment
as well.
I'll come to connectivity, you know, enable my you art to hear.
I said it to asynchronous mode.
This.
Okay, next week.
We come to system, Cole says.
And then we're going to change to time.
Bass over here says The time BS assisting.
We're going to change it to a different timer.
You can select you can nominate timer two or three.
Oh, just like three over here.
And debug, of course, you can live it or you can just like this for a while.
It's fine.
So we can go ahead and configure our you were free ATA's and then we can see how to add things like
tasks and the other artists component.
So I'll just open this again and then I'll bring this up like this.
So these are the configuration of the, um, of the kennel.
We can, um, we can still change this in the, um, in the generated code like we see for other drivers.
When you generate the code from here and you go to your development environment, you still have the
option to be able to change it manually.
We can do that.
Um, this is tasks.
We can add tasks.
It says over here there's a default task task named for task.
And we give the priority of the task.
Always priority normal.
And then over here that and there is the, um, the entry function starts defrauds task, et cetera.
We're going to add a task over here.
I'm just gonna call this thread one.
Remember, thread and tasks are used interchangeably.
If you want the definition, that thread is a task in execution when a task start to execute and we
call it a threat.
So we can use the two words interchange so we can live the parameters here the same way.
Um, entry function we can just call it.
Of course, thread one funk for function.
OK.
They're stuck.
We can leave it there.
Oh, God, another one call this thread, too, but you can give them any names you want to make a bit
more descriptive.
And then entry function through it to function.
And then I say, okay, like this next we are going to add a new tax and new tax means mutual exclusive.
And what this allows is, is that it's allows us to use a shared resource effectively, not even efficiently,
but effectively.
And the reason that is important is if we have two threads trying to write out a you out at the same
time.
Yeah.
There you are today.
Hardware driver, which is the unit, which is the shared resource might crush, is the same thing with
an LCD screen.
If you have two threads and they're all trying to access this single resource at the same time, it
could cause a crash.
What we have to do in this case is to provide AMMU text such as such that one thread would access it
and then when it's done, the other one would access it as well.
So you want to use that here?
Click mutex click out of here.
Our shared resource in this example is is um.
Is the is the U.
R.
So we can give it, um, our new text and name.
You add new text.
If we had LCD, we can um give it the similar name so I'll click.
Okay.
Here like this.
So once this is done we can go ahead and generate our code.
Come to project management over here.
Slimer to change them.
Thirty two qad.
I'll call this.
Free ATA's.
I want to give it a descriptive name.
Tasks and new ticks.
OK.
About the.
And we can live to the heap size and the stock size, the same should be enough.
When I click it generate.
So this is our project.
I'm going to clean up a bit.
I'm going to reduce the number of comment here.
So this whole project with the M the number of comments reduced.
OK, this what we have, we have the, um, the threat I.D., the threat we created.
Each one was given an I.D..
So this is threat one Hondo and it's off type threat I.D. threat to handle it also of type threat I.D.
as well as our new techs that you are to mutex Hondo.
Then this is the default threat that we saw in Cuba mix.
So a threat is basically a main function.
And what I mean by main function is a function with an infinite loop, a function that doesn't return
a function with a well, one loop.
So if we go to the threat functions, we'll see that, uh, functions with infinite loops.
So this is our threat, one func that we created in Cuba.
Max, you can see this is an infinite loop.
This is another way of writing filed one.
And then it has a delay of one here.
This is the code generated by Cuba mix.
This is this the same thing for threat two.
And this is the one for the start, the fourth threat, a default threat or tasks that we saw.
Okay.
And over here, often if you generate code with Cuba, mix without using the free our total without
changing in time.
Base system is the time base.
But because we change our time base to time, a three time a three is known as time base.
And the reason that is, is that the always colonel of free artosis use insisted the real time or preachin
system needs a time or two to work as well.
So with what we are using essayistic for that.
And we need another time for our normal hardware initialization, et cetera.
Some hardware, uh, parts or some hardware modules such as the S.P.I and I to see during initialization,
you need to apply delay every now and then.
We need something to generate such delays for us.
And over here, we're using time on three to do that.
And this whole ink tick is the heartbeat of this other time.
So this is how our delay, if we call it how delay, is going to be used in this.
This is will be January 10, the delay using this whole ink tick.
But before that, it was done using the cystic timer.
Now, is this done using time or three?
And this is because the cystic timer is being used by a war free ATA's operating system.
Right.
So we have our task functions through all of them.
We saw in Cuba mix there was a default Tasco threat created and we added two more.
So one way to see, um, if I wore one, you work on which Archos.
One thing you have to do is, um, profile the task in some, um, in some I.D..
There is a way to know if a task is running or not.
If if you don't have any such I.D. or if the I.D. doesn't provide that, we can find a way of profiling
and we can profile simply using a counter variable.
So what I'm gonna do is create a typedef l.c typedef C task profiler.
And then this is simply you in 32 on a score.
What typedef does is TYPEDEF allows me to use this new name in place of you in 32 to honor Scotties
whenever I want to type.
You intended to underscore to you I can simply type this.
So then I'm going to declare three you in 32 underscore ts.
Call this thread one.
I'll see a thread, one profiler, and then I'll have to read to profiler.
And these are just controvert was just given them fancy names and then we'll have defrauds thread.
Default threat profile.
And what were you going to do is we going to drop these controvert boats in each of the threads or tasks
so that when we execute one to see all of them increment, if all of them are incremented India almost
the same value.
This would tell us that our Real-Time operating system is running and also it is running in a Round-Robin
fashion.
Um, this is not the red one.
This is the red one.
Is this over here.
And through threat to.
Is this over here?
Changed this to two.
I'm going to comment on the delay function and I'm gonna comment on the delay functioning third one
as well.
I'm going to fetch the Ford.
From up here.
And I'm going to police it, you know.
He fought through it.
Okay.
And one thing I should also point out is that over here, they're free ARTUS API is wrapped around what
is known as The Sims is always API.
So if you, uh, if you've ever code it free Arktos or if you've just caught it free ATA's US, it is
written indeed documentation.
The function for creating a new thread is not always through it.
Def this function is a function coming from the CMC is um this fall here Simms's underscore or is not
h free.
Arktos has other functions, just the um CMC is has written a wrapper around that such that we can use
this generic, this generic function always thread def and then um always through thread create such
that when you are using the free R Toscano or D Kyle R t x kando you can use the same functions to quote
your ATA's um your artosis them but different Kandos.
So all the red creates here is the same for free r Toscano or call our tax code.
Our taxes are not a good realtime operating system or Real-Time operating system canno.
So the wrapper function the Sims is always gives us, allows us to be able to use the same API calls
but different Kano's essentially if you do not understand this.
Live it in the questions and uh, questions and answers area.
Now get back to you.
Okay.
So now that we've, um, I out profiler's, let's build our project and see a click over here to build.
Right.
The reason we have this arrow is the position of this, you know why using TYPEDEF.
So this is the type we want to rename it to this new this new word.
So that is why.
And because of that, we have another arrow here.
So typedef, we want to rename or be able to use Taske profiler whenever we want to.
See you in 30 to underscore T..
Okay.
Click here to build.
OK.
We have one warning.
Let's see.
OK.
From this day forward, threat profile.
We want to increment or put a plus plus here.
OK.
So quick to build again.
Okay.
This was built successfully.
Click here to go to debug.
And then also like this.
I say, okay, over here.
Right.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm going to other profilers, to our global to our life expressions when I'm
going to take this out.
This is from a previous project.
I'm gonna come over here controversy to copy and then I'll paste.
And then I'll get tasked to profile us, work on cruzi to copy.
Sorry about that.
Paste.
And then I'll get this last one.
OK, so what is going to happen next?
I'm simply going to click here to run quick to run and what we have we have currently is just a what
default threat profile are running.
Right.
And this is according to a.
This would be according to the centers of our real time operating system.
Currently as it is.
And, um, the reason we have this is.
Shown over here.
I want to show this to Windows so I can post this right.
So we have just this run in.
And the reason we know it's running is because the counter variable is incrementing threat.
One threat to the air stagnant.
Okay.
Let's go to the part where we created a task.
Okay, so over here we created, what, two tasks?
This is the default task.
We left it as it is, as it was in Cuba.
Makes the priority of this one is always priority normal.
And this is our third one.
The priority of this one is always priority.
I do.
This is what the right to the priority is.
Always priority.
I do.
So by this priority, normal has a higher priority than always priority.
That is why only this threat, which is known as start default to task.
And this same threats profile is the default threat profiles.
That is why you really want running these.
I do threats.
The lower frequency.
They've got lower priorities.
Therefore, the the the such law doesn't give them any time to run at all.
So how about we change the priority and we set all of them to always priority normal of this?
And I'm gonna say this and then I'm going to piece this over here.
Let's see what we get a click over here to build.
It's built successfully.
Click here to go to debug.
It's open in.
I see.
I'm gonna minimize this.
Welcome come to live expressions here, um, it says we've got to do this again.
I'll do the next removal and then this is a third one profiler.
A copy this.
It over here.
Copy.
Throw it to profiler.
All right, over here, as well as this copy of it over here.
Okay, I'm going to click here to run.
And now, as you can see there or running, and you have almost the same volume.
So this is what is known as Round-Robin scheduling.
And what Round-Robin means is we allocate equal amount of time for each thread to run.
So say if we've allocated ten milliseconds for each thread thread, one is going to run for ten milliseconds
and then it's going to be put on hold.
Oh, well, we call this as the thread is going to switch the right switch.
I would switch from third one and go to thread to the right to also run for two or for the same amount
of time, which is 10 Emmis.
And then the other one would run.
And this is known as Round-Robin, such that they run for equal amount of time.
And because that is the case, that is how come the counter variable is almost equal.
Because they are run in four equal amounts of time.
And we saw what we call it when the when the priority levels were different.
If you have them in different priority levels, then they don't have the same priority.
So did they need no run at exactly the same rate?
Okay.
So this is, um, our initial experiment for our free.
Our test.
Um, so there's the part one.
We will continue this in the next part.
So I'll see you in the next lesson.
We just continue where we've, uh, we've got to bus.
Well, because the video is getting a bit long.